<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

 <title>Daniel Chia</title>
 <link href="/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
 <link href="/"/>
 <updated>2015-12-16T01:24:25-05:00</updated>
 <id></id>
 <author>
   <name>Daniel Chia</name>
   <email></email>
 </author>

 
 <entry>
   <title>On using Tmux</title>
   <link href="/2015/12/16/tmux-setup/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/12/16/tmux-setup</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;ve been wanting to write this one for a while now. This summer, I got learn two very exciting tools, &lt;strong&gt;Vim&lt;/strong&gt; an &lt;strong&gt;Tmux&lt;/strong&gt;. These two are a must-have for any terminal junkie and together they&amp;#39;ve taken my workflow to a whole new level. Although tmux has some extended functionality, in this post I am going to focus on how I use it in my everyday workflow. 
Also, I am going to assume that you&amp;#39;ve installed the tool on your machine and know how to fire it up. If not, there are plenty of those on the internet. Ok, the big question, what do you customize?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Changing the prefix&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing you ought to do is change the pesky prefix mapping, &lt;strong&gt;CTRL+b&lt;/strong&gt;. To do this, first create your &lt;strong&gt;~/.tmux.conf&lt;/strong&gt; file, this file allows you to configure tmux settings to your liking. In there, add: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot; data-lang=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#prefix to ctrl+a&lt;/span&gt;
unbind C-b
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;set&lt;/span&gt; -g prefix C-a 
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, your pinky finger still has to travel a mile to get to that CTRL key at the bottom left. To fix this, I&amp;#39;d recommend looking into your system and changing the &lt;strong&gt;Caps Lock&lt;/strong&gt; key mapping to &lt;strong&gt;CTRL&lt;/strong&gt;. I have Ubuntu-Gnome, and it came with a nice little piece of software called Tweak Tool, here I was able to turn my Caps Lock key into CTRL.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Refreshing the .tmux.conf file&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Pane Splitting&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we have much nicer prefix &lt;strong&gt;CTRL+a&lt;/strong&gt;, what comes next is pane splitting. The defaults are set to &amp;quot; (vertical) and % (horizontal). These bindings are hard to memorize and not so intuitive, let&amp;#39;s change them. To your &lt;em&gt;.tmux.conf&lt;/em&gt; add:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-sh&quot; data-lang=&quot;sh&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;c&quot;&gt;#intuitive pane splitting&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;bind&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;|&lt;/span&gt; split-window -h -c &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;#{pane_current_path}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;bind&lt;/span&gt; - split-window -v -c &lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;&amp;quot;#{pane_current_path}&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
unbind &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&amp;#39;&amp;quot;&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
unbind %
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wow, that&amp;#39;s a lot of code. Ok, let&amp;#39;s break it down. The first line is saying to use the &lt;strong&gt;|&lt;/strong&gt; key to do a horizontal split. The &lt;em&gt;-c &amp;quot;#{pane&lt;em&gt;current&lt;/em&gt;path}&amp;quot;&lt;/em&gt; part makes it so that the split panes remain in the current path where you split from. Image being into directory that&amp;#39;s 10 levels down, and having to cd there again when you create a new pane. You get the picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Moving between panes&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TODO&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;what do I want to cover&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;-ca mapping
-splitting with | - and making it split current path
-refresh
-using ca ca to move around the panes
-using ca z to zoom into a tmux pane&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Calm and health</title>
   <link href="/2015/12/15/calm-and-balance/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/12/15/calm-and-balance</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s been one heck of a semester. From thinking, &amp;#39;oh it&amp;#39;s going to be fun learning this and that&amp;#39; to &amp;#39;shit, I have to get this and that done&amp;#39;, see the difference, not much fun. While I underestimated the semester&amp;#39;s course load, I&amp;#39;d say that I&amp;#39;ve improved in other aspects. Those being controlling my temper when things go wrong and maintaining a healthy lifestyle. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#39;d like to address the first, my temper. Ever since I can remember i&amp;#39;ve always been a hot-head. I would always act in the spur of the moment, and deal with consequences after. This, of course, always got me into lots of trouble. Now, how does this relate to the present? Well, previously I ranted about being in a leadership position and having a hard time getting others to do their part. Although it&amp;#39;s been a frustrating experience, I have learned that nothing good comes out of agitating myself further and that I have to deal with things in a calm manner and try not to break walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/desk_flip.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Fliptable&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While learning to maintain calm in situations of high stress, I have also learned the importance of my health. It hasn&amp;#39;t been the best year for me in terms of health. I got a severe injury that has prevented me from going into the gym to lift weights and will remain that way for the next couple of months. As much as this sucks, I can&amp;#39;t do anything. Maintaining good health is crucial to suceed in others aspects of life. Just as easily as it has taken me out of the weight room, it can do so as well for everyday tasks that I take for granted. Health comes above all else. &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Leadership is hard</title>
   <link href="/2015/12/03/leadership/"/>
   <updated>2015-12-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/12/03/leadership</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This semester I had to partake in 2 group projects. Both of which I ended up taking leadership roles in, AKA Project Management. Up until now, other than writing I haven&amp;#39;t really collaborated much on any other type of project. For this 2 projects, one of them involved mostly writing and the second was software collaboration. I can&amp;#39;t say that it has been easy nor I&amp;#39;ve done a great job at it, all I can say is that is tough and much improvement is needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#39;s tough because being a leader means that you have to lead by example. What do I mean? If the leader (me) works hard, the rest of the group will follow right? This doesn&amp;#39;t necessarily work all the time as some people tend to take advantage and decide to not contribute at all, knowing that you&amp;#39;ll be there to pick up the slack. But I might&amp;#39;ve missed something here, besides showing yourself as capable. That isn&amp;#39;t enough, you have to delegate tasks. These are the kind of people that won&amp;#39;t do work unless you nudge them too. Yeah, it&amp;#39;s extremely annoying. But to save yourself some grief and avoid overworking yourself, you have to be assertive and demand work from others as it is their responsibility just as much as it is yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other things that I&amp;#39;ve noticed are that as a leader, you need to provide a sense of direction. This is very important if you have very passive team members whom will solely rely on you to provide them with work to do. If it was up to me, I&amp;#39;d take initiative and start improvising things on my own. Sadly, not everyone shares the same mindset. You&amp;#39;re stunt when somebody asks, &amp;quot;what do I do?&amp;quot;. And even after you feel that you have a grasp on direction, an open mind is necessary because feedback is extremely important as the project develops. Your teammates might notice something amiss, and you have to take that into account and not ignore them, like I&amp;#39;ve done.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has been a tough experience, and one that isn&amp;#39;t totally over. As bad as it sounds, I still believe that I&amp;#39;m capable of leadership and it is just something that I need to keep working on. I gotta take in everything calmly and not just rage when everything goes wrong and out of place.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 
 <entry>
   <title>Being dumb, painful Jekyll setup</title>
   <link href="/2015/11/27/being-dumb/"/>
   <updated>2015-11-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
   <id>/2015/11/27/being-dumb</id>
   <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Incredibly annoyed that it took me so long to set things up with jekyll here.
I began customization through the index page, making edits to the html and every darn time I restarted the server, the changes would never go through. It was by chance that I decided to mess with the &lt;strong&gt;_config.yml&lt;/strong&gt; file and found that some parameters defined here were being passed to the index. This meant that no matter how many times I changed the html itself, it would just get replaced, every single time. I stupidly googled &amp;quot;jekyll not saving changes&amp;quot; too. All I can say is...&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/public/img/facepalm.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Facepalm&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
 </entry>
 

</feed>
